<topics task="2021 TREC Clinical Trials">
    <topic number="1"> A 19-year-old male came to clinic with some sexual concern. He recently engaged in a relationship and is worried about the satisfaction of his girlfriend. He has a "baby face" according to his girlfriend's statement and he is not as muscular as his classmates. On physical examination, there is some pubic hair and poorly developed secondary sexual characteristics. He is unable to detect coffee smell during the examination, but the visual acuity is normal. Ultrasound reveals the testes volume of 1-2 ml. The hormonal evaluation showed serum testosterone level of 65 ng/dL with low levels of GnRH. </topic>
    <topic number="2"> A 32-year-old woman comes to the hospital with vaginal spotting. Her last menstrual period was 10 weeks ago. She has regular menses lasting for 6 days and repeating every 29 days. Medical history is significant for appendectomy and several complicated UTIs. She has multiple male partners, and she is inconsistent with using barrier contraceptives. Vital signs are normal. Serum β-hCG level is 1800 mIU/mL, and a repeat level after 2 days shows an abnormal rise to 2100 mIU/mL. Pelvic ultrasound reveals a thin endometrium with no gestational sac in the uterus. </topic>
    <topic number="3"> A 51-year-old man comes to the office complaining of fatigue and some sexual problems including lack of libido. The patient doesn't smoke or use any illicit drug. Blood pressure is 120/80 mm Hg and pulse is 70/min. Oxygen saturation is 99% on room air. BMI is 24 kg/m2. Skin examination shows increased pigmentation. Genotype testing is consistent with homozygosity for the C282Y mutation. Laboratory study shows transferrin saturation of 55% and serum ferritin of 550 μg/L. He is diagnosed as a case of hemochromatosis. </topic>
    <topic number="4"> A 66-year-old woman comes to the office due to joint pain in the hands and periodic morning stiffness that lasts less than 15 minutes. The pain is moderately severe and worsens with daily activity. The patient used Tylenol with minimal relief. Past medical history is notable for hypertension and hypercholesteremia. Physical examination shows firm nodules over the distal interphalangeal joints, bilaterally. The patient has pain in her knees as well. The knees are stiff in the morning for less than 30 minutes and become worse with climbing stairs. She has some sensation of bone friction during activity. X-ray shows narrowing of the joint space, subchondral bone sclerosis and osteophyte formation along the joints. </topic>
    <topic number="5"> A 23-year-old man comes to the emergency department following an episode of syncope. He was working out when he felt dizzy and passed out without head injury. He has had 3 other episodes of light-headedness over the last year, all happening during physical activity. He never had this experience while resting. He has no other medical conditions. The patient does not use tobacco, alcohol, or illicit drugs. His father died suddenly at age 35. Vital signs are within normal limits. On physical examination, the patient has a harsh systolic murmur. The lungs are clear with no peripheral edema. Echocardiography shows asymmetric interventricular septal hypertrophy. </topic>
    <topic number="6"> A 61-year-old man comes to the clinic due to nonproductive cough and progressive dyspnea. The patient's medical conditions include hypertension, hypercholesteremia and peptic ulcer disease. He smokes 2 packs of cigarettes daily for the past 30 years. On examination, there are decreased breath sounds and percussive dullness at the base of the left lung. Other vital signs are normal. Abdomen is soft without tenderness. CT scan shows a left-sided pleural effusion and nodular thickening of the pleura. The plural fluid was bloody on thoracentesis. Biopsy shows proliferation of epithelioid-type cells with very long microvilli. </topic>
    <topic number="7"> A 3-year-old girl is brought to the clinic by her parents for assessment of her short stature. Physical examination reveals short limbs and a relatively large head. She has a flat nasal bridge and a small midface. The girl's father exhibits similar physical features; however, her mother looks normal. The genetic testing reveals an autosomal dominant point mutation in the fibroblast growth factor receptor 3 (FGFR3) gene consistent with achondroplasia in both father and the child. The girl has not received any treatment yet, and it is her first visit after immigration to the US. The other mental and developmental examinations are unremarkable. </topic>
    <topic number="8"> A 7-month-old boy is brought to emergency by his parents due to irritability and inability to defecate for the past 3 days. The patient has had constipation and discomfort with bowel movements since birth. His symptoms worsened after eating semi-solid foods. Vital signs are normal. Abdominal examination shows distension and tenderness to palpation with presence of bowel sounds. Xray with barium shows a narrow rectum and rectosigmoid area. The rest of the colon proximal to this segment is dilated. Digital rectal exam revealed burst of feces out of the anus. The biopsy showed absence of submucosal ganglia in the last segment of the large intestine. </topic>
    <topic number="9"> A 67-year-old woman comes to the clinic due to recent episode of choking, dysphagia, and cough. Her other medical problems include hypertension, dyslipidemia, and osteoarthritis. She does not smoke or use alcohol. She lives with her husband and she is able to do her own daily activities. She used to teach elementary school. Blood pressure is 135/80 mm Hg. The patient's breath smells bad. Other physical examinations are normal. A barium swallow study reveals an abnormality in the upper esophagus with an outpouching at the junction of the lower part of the throat and the upper portion of the esophagus. </topic>
    <topic number="10"> A 19-year-old girl comes to the clinic due to a left wrist mass. She noticed swelling on the top of her wrist about 4 months ago and came to the clinic due to cosmetic concerns. Examination shows a nontender, rounded mass on the dorsal wrist that transilluminates with a penlight. Vital signs are normal. The patient needs to type on her computer almost all day. She is left-handed. She does not smoke or use illicit drugs. She is in sexual relationship with two male partners and uses condoms. </topic>
</topics>