<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on April 27, 2021</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04842669</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>REC/00864 Kirran Sikandar</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04842669</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effects of Low Level Laser Therapy On Exercise Induced Muscle Damage in Wrist Flexors Of Untrained Young Adults</brief_title>
  <official_title>Effects of Low Level Laser Therapy On Exercise Induced Muscle Damage in Wrist Flexors Of Untrained Young Adults.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Riphah International University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Riphah International University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The main aim of the current study is to investigate the effects of Low-level Laser Therapy on&#xD;
      exercise-induced muscle damage of wrist flexors in untrained young adults. A randomized&#xD;
      controlled trial will be conducted at Sargodha Medical College, University of Sargodha. The&#xD;
      sample size calculated is 16. The participants will be divided into two equal group; 1)&#xD;
      Interventional group (Low level laser therapy), 2) Control group (conventional) each having 8&#xD;
      participants. The study duration will be six months after approval from Research board.&#xD;
      Blocked randomization sampling technique will be used. The subjects will be randomly assigned&#xD;
      to any of the interventional or control group. Interventional group will further be allocated&#xD;
      to prophylactic or therapeutic group. Only Un-trained young Adults, Aged 19-25&#xD;
      (under-graduate/college and university students) without gender discrimination will be&#xD;
      included in the study. Tools used in the study will be TALAG Scale (Soreness assessment),&#xD;
      Goniometer (ROM), Algometer (Pressure¬-pain Threshold), Electronic digital hand Dynamometer&#xD;
      (Grip Strength) and PRS (Perceived Recovery Status Scale). Data will be collected at&#xD;
      baseline, 1hr, 24hr, 72hr, 96hr, 120hr, 148hr, 168hr and 192 hrs after the induction&#xD;
      protocol.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Wrist flexors play a crucial role in hand function. This group of small muscles is of high&#xD;
      importance in our day to day tasks like carrying heavy objects and for activities in which&#xD;
      forceful and/or rapid wrist flexions are required. Apart from this, the wrist flexors have a&#xD;
      distinctive neural control as compared to the other surrounding musculature.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Muscle exhaustion that is induced after eccentric exercise, can either be of acute onset or&#xD;
      delayed onset. Exercise induced muscle soreness that persists for about 4 to 6 hours before&#xD;
      it returns to pre-exercise level is termed as acute soreness. On the other hand, muscle&#xD;
      soreness beginning at 8 to 24 hours after eccentric exercise, with peak level at 24 to 48&#xD;
      hours is known as delayed soreness. Delayed-Onset Muscle Soreness (DOMS) is a common&#xD;
      neuromuscular condition characterized by increased sensitivity to pain that is apparent with&#xD;
      unaccustomed or vigorous exercise, a day after performance. DOMS becomes evident about 6-8&#xD;
      hours after an intense exercise bout and peaks at approximately 24-72 hours post-exercise.&#xD;
      During first few hours of intensive exercise metabolism get disturbed that leads to&#xD;
      inefficient physical activity and performance. Prolonged metabolic disturbances and physical&#xD;
      activity and performance impairment progressing to days ultimately induce tissue damage that&#xD;
      we call as delayed-onset muscle soreness. Event that produces muscle soreness is suggested as&#xD;
      a mechanical disruption of sarcomeres leading to swelling of injured muscle fibers thus&#xD;
      initiating an inflammatory response leading to the excitement of nociceptors.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Exercise-induced muscle injury is similar in pathological change and pathogenic mechanism in&#xD;
      humans and animals. Human beings and animals have shown parallel reactions to changes caused&#xD;
      by muscle damage induced by eccentric exercises. The beginning of initial exercise-induced&#xD;
      muscle damage may be draining but is pain free. Later on, after 8-24 hours of muscle damage&#xD;
      initiation, the subsequent inflammation results in delayed onset of muscle soreness.&#xD;
&#xD;
      It has been assumed that whenever an un-habitual physical exercise is carried out by a person&#xD;
      then muscle injury occurs. A high level of muscle injury is associated with eccentric&#xD;
      activities. Muscle injury is more likely to occur in untrained individuals who start&#xD;
      practicing exercise. Furthermore, incidence of muscle injury is more common with exercises&#xD;
      involving eccentric activities. Loss of strength, muscle inflammation, high level of muscle&#xD;
      proteins in blood and delayed onset of muscle soreness DOMS are considered to be the expected&#xD;
      outcomes of muscle injury. Different electro-physical modalities are being used by Physical&#xD;
      therapists. In many conditions, improved healing and functioning are achieved by the use of&#xD;
      these electro-physical modalities. Some animal studies have also reported the positive role&#xD;
      of Low-Level Laser Therapy, when used in optimal parameters of irradiations, in enhancing the&#xD;
      muscle healing and decreasing inflammation. Increased amount and activity of mitochondria and&#xD;
      increased cross-sectional area of muscle fiber is associated with training. Increased muscle&#xD;
      mass and improved mitochondrial function result in shift in muscle fiber type composition,&#xD;
      from type two B to type Two A, and an increase in local glycogen storage capability. These&#xD;
      combined adaptations make specialized athletes chiefly different from untrained people.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Several studies performed on human and animals evidenced the action of Low-level Laser&#xD;
      Therapy in achieving therapeutic and physiological effects involving improvement of muscle&#xD;
      functioning through interaction with biological tissues. Decrease in muscle fatigue has been&#xD;
      reported by several researchers with the application of Laser Therapy before exercises that&#xD;
      induces fatigue while considerable functional enhancement has also been evidenced by some&#xD;
      investigators with Laser application after performing fatigue inducing exercises. Therapeutic&#xD;
      effect of LLLT may be explained by mechanisms involving improved microcirculation of tissue,&#xD;
      anti-inflammatory effect, decreased oxidative stress and decrease in tissue ischemia.&#xD;
&#xD;
      In 2016, a study was conducted to evaluate the effects of low level laser therapy on post&#xD;
      exercise recovery of skeletal muscle and improvement in muscle performance and function. The&#xD;
      conclusion of this study was that pre-exercise treatment with low level laser therapy&#xD;
      increases muscle performance along with improvement in biochemical markers associated with&#xD;
      inflammation and muscle injury.&#xD;
&#xD;
      In August 2011, Wouber Hérickson de Brito and fellows carried out a comparative study to&#xD;
      investigate whether muscle performance could be increased with endurance training associated&#xD;
      with LLLT when compared to the same training without LLLT. Results suggested a great decrease&#xD;
      in fatigue when training was combined with LLLT, thus improving the muscle performance.&#xD;
&#xD;
      In August 2010, a study was carried out to find out the effectiveness of low-level laser&#xD;
      therapy (LLLT) on muscle performance, fatigue development, and biochemical markers of&#xD;
      post-exercise recovery on bicep muscle. Results clearly suggested that endurance for&#xD;
      repetitive elbow flexion has been increased with the application of LLLT before exercise&#xD;
      while levels of reactive protein, creatine kinase and blood lactate has been decreased after&#xD;
      performance of exercise.&#xD;
&#xD;
      In July 2010, to investigate the effects of Low-level laser therapy before eccentric exercise&#xD;
      on muscle damage markers in humans. It was concluded that LLLT therapy when given before&#xD;
      performance of eccentric exercise, accelerated the increase of muscle proteins in the blood&#xD;
      serum and the decrease in muscle force.&#xD;
&#xD;
      In July 2011, a study was carried out to compare the effects of Red (660 nm) and infrared&#xD;
      (830 nm) low-level laser therapy in skeletal muscle fatigue in humans. The study showed that&#xD;
      both red and infrared LLLT are effective in delaying the development skeletal muscle fatigue&#xD;
      and in improvement of skeletal functioning.&#xD;
&#xD;
      In August 2009, to investigate the Effects of Low-Level Laser Irradiation on Skeletal Muscle&#xD;
      Injury after Eccentric Exercise. It was the first study performed on animal model to&#xD;
      investigate these effects. It was concluded that Low-level He-Ne laser therapy exerts&#xD;
      therapeutic effects by improving anti-oxidative capacity of muscle as well as decreasing the&#xD;
      inﬂammatory reaction.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">August 1, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Numeric pain rating scale (NPRS):</measure>
    <time_frame>8 days</time_frame>
    <description>The Numeric Rating Scale is an 11 point scale where the end points are the extremes of no pain and pain as bad as it could be, or worst pain. Numerical Rating Scale has good sensitivity and generates data that can be statistically analyzed for audit purposes</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>TALAG Scale (Soreness assessment):</measure>
    <time_frame>8 days</time_frame>
    <description>TALAG scale will be used to assess the perceived soreness. It consists of points 1-7 on scale. The minimum level 1 with no pain and a maximum point 7 with unbearably painful</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Goniometer</measure>
    <time_frame>8 days</time_frame>
    <description>Physical therapists widely use goniometer for measurement of different joint ranges to evaluate any ROM limitation. The universal full circle goniometer is the preferred instrument for measuring ROM</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Pressure-pain Threshold by Algometer</measure>
    <time_frame>8 days</time_frame>
    <description>Algometer is a reliable tool for measuring pressure pain threshold(22).The Pressure Pain Threshold will be evaluated using an analogue algometer (Baseline, 60 pounds capacity) by applying vertical pressure. To stimulate the participant's pain, the pressure will be increased at a rate of 1kg/cm2.Measurements will be taken pre and post treatment for 2 times during study</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Electronic digital hand Dynamometer</measure>
    <time_frame>8 days</time_frame>
    <description>Grip strength will be evaluated with an electronic digital hand dynamometer as per recommendations</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Perceived Recovery (Perceived Recovery Status Scale):</measure>
    <time_frame>8 days</time_frame>
    <description>PRS scale is a convenient, noninvasive marker of recovery relative to subsequent training. This scale consist of 10 points from 0 -10 with the minimum value 0 for very poorly recovered and maximum 10 value for very well recovered</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">16</enrollment>
  <condition>Wrist Injuries</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Low level laser therapy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Low level laser therapy</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Conservative treatment</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Conservative treatment</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>low level laser therapy</intervention_name>
    <description>Endo-laser 422 with interchangeable laser probes will be used for the purpose. It is a 2-channel unit and is software operated. For treatment of small surfaces with mono laser there are diodes of 25, 100 and 500 milliWatt.Frequency will be adjusted to 500 Hz, dose 0.1/cm2 with time duration of 1-5 minutes.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Low level laser therapy</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Conservative treatment</intervention_name>
    <description>(Topical ibuprofen gel) for muscle soreness will be provided</description>
    <arm_group_label>Conservative treatment</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Un-trained young Adults&#xD;
&#xD;
        Exclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Any Trauma&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Any psychological condition&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Participation in any scheduled Physical training&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Athlete population&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Use of any nutritional supplement&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>19 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>25 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Maria Khalid, MSOMPT</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Riphah International University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Imran Amjad, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>03324390125</phone>
    <email>imran.amjad@riphah.edu.pk</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Sargodha Medical College (University of Sargodha)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Sargodha</city>
        <state>Punjab</state>
        <zip>46000</zip>
        <country>Pakistan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Maria khalid, MSOMPT</last_name>
      <phone>03315369768</phone>
      <email>maria.khalid@riphah.edu.pk</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>kiran sikander, MSOMPT*</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Pakistan</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Behrens M, Husmann F, Mau-Moeller A, Schlegel J, Reuter EM, Zschorlich VR. Neuromuscular Properties of the Human Wrist Flexors as a Function of the Wrist Joint Angle. Front Bioeng Biotechnol. 2019 Aug 21;7:181. doi: 10.3389/fbioe.2019.00181. eCollection 2019.</citation>
    <PMID>31497595</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Isabell WK, Durrant E, Myrer W, Anderson S. The effects of ice massage, ice massage with exercise, and exercise on the prevention and treatment of delayed onset muscle soreness. J Athl Train. 1992;27(3):208-17.</citation>
    <PMID>16558163</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Khamwong P, Paungmali A, Pirunsan U, Joseph L. Prophylactic Effects of Sauna on Delayed-Onset Muscle Soreness of the Wrist Extensors. Asian J Sports Med. 2015 Jun;6(2):e25549. doi: 10.5812/asjsm.6(2)2015.25549. Epub 2015 Jun 20.</citation>
    <PMID>26446307</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Leal Junior EC, Lopes-Martins RA, Baroni BM, De Marchi T, Taufer D, Manfro DS, Rech M, Danna V, Grosselli D, Generosi RA, Marcos RL, Ramos L, Bjordal JM. Effect of 830 nm low-level laser therapy applied before high-intensity exercises on skeletal muscle recovery in athletes. Lasers Med Sci. 2009 Nov;24(6):857-63. doi: 10.1007/s10103-008-0633-4. Epub 2008 Dec 5.</citation>
    <PMID>19057981</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Herbert RD, de Noronha M, Kamper SJ. Stretching to prevent or reduce muscle soreness after exercise. Cochrane Database Syst Rev. 2011 Jul 6;(7):CD004577. doi: 10.1002/14651858.CD004577.pub3. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>21735398</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Liu XG, Zhou YJ, Liu TC, Yuan JQ. Effects of low-level laser irradiation on rat skeletal muscle injury after eccentric exercise. Photomed Laser Surg. 2009 Dec;27(6):863-9. doi: 10.1089/pho.2008.2443.</citation>
    <PMID>19697999</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Aver Vanin A, De Marchi T, Tomazoni SS, Tairova O, Leão Casalechi H, de Tarso Camillo de Carvalho P, Bjordal JM, Leal-Junior EC. Pre-Exercise Infrared Low-Level Laser Therapy (810 nm) in Skeletal Muscle Performance and Postexercise Recovery in Humans, What Is the Optimal Dose? A Randomized, Double-Blind, Placebo-Controlled Clinical Trial. Photomed Laser Surg. 2016 Oct;34(10):473-482. Epub 2016 Aug 29.</citation>
    <PMID>27575834</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Baroni BM, Leal Junior EC, De Marchi T, Lopes AL, Salvador M, Vaz MA. Low level laser therapy before eccentric exercise reduces muscle damage markers in humans. Eur J Appl Physiol. 2010 Nov;110(4):789-96. doi: 10.1007/s00421-010-1562-z. Epub 2010 Jul 3.</citation>
    <PMID>20602109</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Felismino AS, Costa EC, Aoki MS, Ferraresi C, de Araújo Moura Lemos TM, de Brito Vieira WH. Effect of low-level laser therapy (808 nm) on markers of muscle damage: a randomized double-blind placebo-controlled trial. Lasers Med Sci. 2014 May;29(3):933-8. doi: 10.1007/s10103-013-1430-2. Epub 2013 Sep 5.</citation>
    <PMID>24005882</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Leal Junior EC, Lopes-Martins RA, Frigo L, De Marchi T, Rossi RP, de Godoi V, Tomazoni SS, Silva DP, Basso M, Filho PL, de Valls Corsetti F, Iversen VV, Bjordal JM. Effects of low-level laser therapy (LLLT) in the development of exercise-induced skeletal muscle fatigue and changes in biochemical markers related to postexercise recovery. J Orthop Sports Phys Ther. 2010 Aug;40(8):524-32. doi: 10.2519/jospt.2010.3294.</citation>
    <PMID>20436237</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chapman MA, Arif M, Emanuelsson EB, Reitzner SM, Lindholm ME, Mardinoglu A, Sundberg CJ. Skeletal Muscle Transcriptomic Comparison between Long-Term Trained and Untrained Men and Women. Cell Rep. 2020 Jun 23;31(12):107808. doi: 10.1016/j.celrep.2020.107808.</citation>
    <PMID>32579934</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Toma RL, Tucci HT, Antunes HK, Pedroni CR, de Oliveira AS, Buck I, Ferreira PD, Vassão PG, Renno AC. Effect of 808 nm low-level laser therapy in exercise-induced skeletal muscle fatigue in elderly women. Lasers Med Sci. 2013 Sep;28(5):1375-82. doi: 10.1007/s10103-012-1246-5. Epub 2013 Jan 8.</citation>
    <PMID>23296713</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dos Reis FA, da Silva BA, Laraia EM, de Melo RM, Silva PH, Leal-Junior EC, de Carvalho Pde T. Effects of pre- or post-exercise low-level laser therapy (830 nm) on skeletal muscle fatigue and biochemical markers of recovery in humans: double-blind placebo-controlled trial. Photomed Laser Surg. 2014 Feb;32(2):106-12. doi: 10.1089/pho.2013.3617. Epub 2014 Jan 23.</citation>
    <PMID>24456143</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Vieira WH, Ferraresi C, Perez SE, Baldissera V, Parizotto NA. Effects of low-level laser therapy (808 nm) on isokinetic muscle performance of young women submitted to endurance training: a randomized controlled clinical trial. Lasers Med Sci. 2012 Mar;27(2):497-504. doi: 10.1007/s10103-011-0984-0. Epub 2011 Aug 26.</citation>
    <PMID>21870127</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>de Almeida P, Lopes-Martins RA, De Marchi T, Tomazoni SS, Albertini R, Corrêa JC, Rossi RP, Machado GP, da Silva DP, Bjordal JM, Leal Junior EC. Red (660 nm) and infrared (830 nm) low-level laser therapy in skeletal muscle fatigue in humans: what is better? Lasers Med Sci. 2012 Mar;27(2):453-8. doi: 10.1007/s10103-011-0957-3. Epub 2011 Jul 22.</citation>
    <PMID>21814736</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Williamson A, Hoggart B. Pain: a review of three commonly used pain rating scales. J Clin Nurs. 2005 Aug;14(7):798-804. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>16000093</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gajdosik RL, Bohannon RW. Clinical measurement of range of motion. Review of goniometry emphasizing reliability and validity. Phys Ther. 1987 Dec;67(12):1867-72.</citation>
    <PMID>3685114</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Laurent CM, Green JM, Bishop PA, Sjökvist J, Schumacker RE, Richardson MT, Curtner-Smith M. A practical approach to monitoring recovery: development of a perceived recovery status scale. J Strength Cond Res. 2011 Mar;25(3):620-8. doi: 10.1519/JSC.0b013e3181c69ec6.</citation>
    <PMID>20581704</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hyldahl RD, Keadle J, Rouzier PA, Pearl D, Clarkson PM. Effects of ibuprofen topical gel on muscle soreness. Med Sci Sports Exerc. 2010 Mar;42(3):614-21. doi: 10.1249/MSS.0b013e3181b95db2.</citation>
    <PMID>19952809</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>April 2021</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>April 10, 2021</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 10, 2021</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">April 13, 2021</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 10, 2021</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 10, 2021</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 13, 2021</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>exercise induced muscle damage</keyword>
  <keyword>wrist flexor</keyword>
  <keyword>low level laser therapy</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Wrist Injuries</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

