<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on April 27, 2021</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03986021</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>190110</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>19-E-0110</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03986021</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Reproductive Axis Maturation in the Early Post-Menarchal Years</brief_title>
  <official_title>Reproductive Axis Maturation in the Early Post-Menarchal Years: A Pilot Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute of Environmental Health Sciences (NIEHS)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background:&#xD;
&#xD;
      Most adult women with irregular periods of unknown cause report symptoms dating back to early&#xD;
      adolescence. This study aims to learn how girls periods change in the 2 years after their&#xD;
      first period. This will help researchers learn what healthy puberty looks like and how they&#xD;
      can spot signs of hormone problems early on.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Objective:&#xD;
&#xD;
      To learn how long it takes girls to develop regular menstrual cycles after their first&#xD;
      period.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Eligibility:&#xD;
&#xD;
      Healthy girls ages 8-14.5 who either (1) haven t had their first period but show signs of&#xD;
      puberty, such as breast development and hair in the genital area; or (2) had their first&#xD;
      period in the past 6 months&#xD;
&#xD;
      Design:&#xD;
&#xD;
      A parent or guardian must allow their daughter to participate. They must attend all study&#xD;
      visits with her.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Participants will first be screened by phone. Those who qualify will be screened in person.&#xD;
      They will have a physical exam. They will give blood and urine samples. They will have an&#xD;
      ultrasound of their abdomen. They will fill out questionnaires. They will sit in a BOD POD&#xD;
      for 6 minutes: This is an egg-shaped machine that takes body measurements.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Participants will have sets of visits at home or at the clinic about every 6 months. The&#xD;
      number of visits in each set will depend on their menstrual cycle. Then they will have a&#xD;
      final visit. Visits will include repeats of the screening tests.&#xD;
&#xD;
      At home, participants will collect their urine daily to measure hormones. They will keep a&#xD;
      diary of their periods.&#xD;
&#xD;
      The study will last about 2 years.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The broad goal of these studies is to determine the physiologic and pathophysiologic&#xD;
      underpinnings of irregular menstrual cycles among adolescents in the early post-menarchal&#xD;
      period. Irregular menstruation affects &gt; 2.5 million reproductive-age women in the US each&#xD;
      year1. Most adult women with oligomenorrhea of unknown etiology reporting symptoms dating&#xD;
      back to early adolescence. While a period of cycle irregularity is well-described in the&#xD;
      first few years after menarche, a lack of understanding of the basic mechanisms of normal&#xD;
      reproductive axis development in the post-menarchal female has hampered our ability to&#xD;
      distinguish abnormal from normal developmental trajectories. Moreover, the commonly held&#xD;
      belief that menstrual irregularity among teenage girls is normal has also delayed detection&#xD;
      of pathology in reproductive development, precluding institution of early preventative&#xD;
      strategies to curtail future reproductive morbidity.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">December 19, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To determine the time from menarche to regular ovulatory cycles, defined as two consecutive ovulatory cycles with normal (10-14 day) luteal phase length.</measure>
    <time_frame>Defined as two consecutive ovulatory cycles with normal (10-14 day) luteal phase length during the first two post-menarchal years</time_frame>
    <description>We hypothesize that the temporal sequence of reproductive maturation will consist of anovulatory cycles (representing a time of unopposed estrogen exposure), ovulatory cycles with a short luteal phase (estrogen with low progesterone exposure), and finally, ovulatory cycles with a normal luteal phase length (estrogen action fully counterbalanced by progesterone action).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">75</enrollment>
  <condition>Reproductive Physiological Processes</condition>
  <condition>Pediatrics</condition>
  <condition>Adolescent Health</condition>
  <condition>Adolescent Developement</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Post-menarche girls</arm_group_label>
    <description>Healthy, early post-menarchal girls age 10-14</description>
  </arm_group>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Healthy early post-menarchal girls age 8 less than or equal to 15 years.&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  Part 1-Pre-menarche monitoring (holding pattern):&#xD;
&#xD;
        INCLUSION CRITERIA:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Age 8-14.5 years old&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Healthy weight, defined as having a body weight &gt;85% of expected (EBW) and a body mass&#xD;
             index (BMI) &lt;99th percentile&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Some breast development&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Pre-menarche&#xD;
&#xD;
        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Taking or planning to take medications that affect reproductive hormones in the next 2&#xD;
             to 3 years (e.g. birth control pills).&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Planning to move more than 60 miles from the CRU within the next 2 years&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Chronic medical condition, including but not limited to diabetes mellitus, congenital&#xD;
             adrenal hyperplasia, cystic fibrosis, sickle cell disease, inflammatory bowel disease,&#xD;
             juvenile rheumatoid arthritis, and lupus.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  First-degree relative with polycystic ovarian syndrome, premature ovarian&#xD;
             insufficiency, hypogonadotropic hypogonadism, or other pubertal development disorder&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Excessive exercise (defined as running &gt;20 miles per week or its equivalent)&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Pregnancy&#xD;
&#xD;
        Part 2 - Post-menarche cycle tracking:&#xD;
&#xD;
        INCLUSION CRITERIA:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Age at menarche 10-14.5 years old&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Healthy weight, defined as having a body weight &gt;85% of expected (EBW) and a body mass&#xD;
             index (BMI) &lt;99th percentile&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Approximately less than or equal to 6 months post-menarchal (will typically have&#xD;
             completed 4 or fewer menstrual cycles)&#xD;
&#xD;
        Biochemical criteria: normal thyroid hormone, prolactin, and testosterone levels&#xD;
&#xD;
        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Taking or planning to take medications that affect reproductive hormones in the next 2&#xD;
             to 3 years (e.g. birth control pills).&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Planning to move more than 60 miles from the CRU within the next 2 years&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Chronic medical condition, including but not limited to diabetes mellitus, congenital&#xD;
             adrenal hyperplasia, cystic fibrosis, sickle cell disease, inflammatory bowel disease,&#xD;
             juvenile rheumatoid arthritis, and lupus.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  First-degree relative with polycystic ovarian syndrome, premature ovarian&#xD;
             insufficiency, hypogonadotropic hypogonadism, or other pubertal development disorder&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Excessive exercise (defined as running &gt;20 miles per week or its equivalent)&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Anemia (defined as hemoglobin &lt;12.0 g/dl)&#xD;
&#xD;
             --Participants with hemoglobin between 11.5 g/dl and 12.0 g/dl may still participate&#xD;
             by providing dried blood spots, or no more than 18ml of blood during any given&#xD;
             interval.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Pregnancy&#xD;
&#xD;
        In some cases, particularly in those participants with short menstrual cycle lengths, the&#xD;
        participant may have her first cycle monitoring visit before the results from all the&#xD;
        laboratory tests from the screening visit are available. Some of these tests take &gt; 5-7&#xD;
        days to complete. The tests are necessary for eligibility but are not related to&#xD;
        participant safety. If the results are abnormal, the participant will be withdrawn from the&#xD;
        study at that time.&#xD;
&#xD;
        If a potential participant meets all eligibility criteria for Part 1 during the initial&#xD;
        phone screening, she and at least one parent or guardian will verbally assent and consent,&#xD;
        respectively, to receive regular communications from the study team (i.e. monthly phone&#xD;
        calls, emails, and text messages. The purpose of these communications is follow-up with the&#xD;
        participant to determine when she can enroll in Part 2 of the study. She will not&#xD;
        participate in any clinical study procedures in Part 2 as detailed below until she has her&#xD;
        first period, at which time she and/or her parent or guardian will notify the study team.&#xD;
        This will allow study staff to enroll girls at the desired (young) gynecological age and&#xD;
        allow initial study visits to be scheduled in alignment with the girls' menstrual cycles.&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>8 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>15 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Natalie D Shaw, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Institute of Environmental Health Sciences (NIEHS)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>NIEHS Join A Study Recruitment Group</last_name>
    <phone>(855) 696-4347</phone>
    <email>myniehs@nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>NIEHS Clinical Research Unit (CRU)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Research Triangle Park</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <zip>27709</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>NIEHS Join A Study Recruitment Group</last_name>
      <phone>855-696-4347</phone>
      <email>myniehs@nih.gov</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>https://clinicalstudies.info.nih.gov/cgi/detail.cgi?A_2019-E-0110.html</url>
    <description>NIH Clinical Center Detailed Web Page</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>April 16, 2021</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 13, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 13, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 14, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 17, 2021</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 17, 2021</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 20, 2021</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Menarche</keyword>
  <keyword>Adolescent</keyword>
  <keyword>Physiology</keyword>
  <keyword>Hormones</keyword>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

