<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on April 27, 2021</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02009345</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>FH Canada</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02009345</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Familial Hypercholesterolemia Canada / Hypercholesterolemie Familiale Canada</brief_title>
  <acronym>FHCanada</acronym>
  <official_title>Familial Hypercholesterolemia Canada / Hypercholesterolemie Familiale Canada</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>McGill University Health Centre/Research Institute of the McGill University Health Centre</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Amgen</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Sanofi</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Pfizer</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Merck Sharp &amp; Dohme Corp.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Aegerion Pharmaceuticals, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>McGill University Health Centre/Research Institute of the McGill University Health Centre</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Familial hypercholesterolemia (FH) is the most frequent genetic lipoprotein disorder&#xD;
      associated with premature CAD. In Canada, the burden of disease is estimated to be&#xD;
      approximately 83,500 patients. The goal of this initiative is to create a registry of&#xD;
      subjects with FH across Canada. Rare diseases of lipoprotein metabolism will also be&#xD;
      included. Using a &quot;hub and spoke&quot; model, the registry will be extended in various communities&#xD;
      to link primary care physicians with provincial academic centers. The registry will include&#xD;
      clinical, biochemical and demographic information. Specimens (plasma/serum and DNA) will be&#xD;
      collected for biobanking. We propose a three-tier registry: local, provincial and&#xD;
      Canada-wide, which will be completely anonymized. The registry will be made available for&#xD;
      clinicians to manage patient care, identify relatives for screening and treatment (cascade&#xD;
      screening), to provide advice to general practitioners and to support collaborative studies&#xD;
      in biomedical, clinical, health outcomes and health economics research. The data extracted&#xD;
      for the provincial portion of the database will allow administrative database research that&#xD;
      will provide important information to key stakeholders and permit allocation of resources. It&#xD;
      will also allow a sound and uniform rationale for the use of novel therapeutic agents and&#xD;
      provide expert advice to regulatory agencies. At the Canadian level, the database will allow&#xD;
      clinicians and researchers to determine the burden of disease and the long-term effects of&#xD;
      treatment. Through the creation of a Canada-wide network of academic clinics, integrating&#xD;
      lipid specialists, endocrinologists and cardiologists, the Canadian FH registry will lead to&#xD;
      significant benefits for FH patients, clinicians and researchers, biopharmaceutical industry&#xD;
      and government.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Familial hypercholesterolemia (FH) is a genetic lipoprotein disorder characterized by&#xD;
      elevations in low-density lipoprotein cholesterol (LDL-C) &gt;95th percentile for age and&#xD;
      gender. Affected individuals may show clinical manifestations (xanthomas, xanthelasmas and&#xD;
      premature arcus corneus) although these manifestations are seen less frequently with early&#xD;
      diagnosis and treatment. Untreated, FH will lead to atherosclerotic cardiovascular disease&#xD;
      (CVD), primarily coronary artery disease (CAD). There are at least three accepted definitions&#xD;
      for FH, based on absolute LDL-C levels (MedPed criteria), the Simon-Broome criteria include a&#xD;
      fixed cut-point for LDL-C, the presence of DNA mutations and xanthomas and the FH Dutch&#xD;
      Criteria (the Netherlands).&#xD;
&#xD;
      There are well-developed FH Registries in the Netherlands, United Kingdom, Spain, France, and&#xD;
      the US, through the newly established US FH Foundation. In the United Kingdom, a report on&#xD;
      the economic advantages of treating FH revealed that lipid-lowering statin therapy would lead&#xD;
      to 101 fewer cardiovascular deaths/1000 patients with FH given treatment. The cost saving&#xD;
      from cardiovascular events is estimated at over $CAN 592 million in the UK if all relatives&#xD;
      of index cases were identified and treated, compared with no treatment given. This cascade&#xD;
      testing strategy has been successfully applied in the Netherlands in families of FH probands&#xD;
      with a detected mutation, thus allowing statin treatment of family members at risk of early&#xD;
      coronary heart disease.&#xD;
&#xD;
      In Canada, the burden of disease is estimated to be approximately 83,500 patients, based on&#xD;
      an allele frequency of 1/500. In the province of Quebec, the allele frequency is&#xD;
      approximately 1/270 and the number of affected subjects is approximately 29,000. Left&#xD;
      untreated, FH men develop cardiovascular disease (CVD) in the third decade of life and women,&#xD;
      in the fourth decade. When identified and treated early, life expectancy is normal.&#xD;
&#xD;
      The purpose of this initiative is to create a registry of subjects with FH across Canada&#xD;
      designed to identify subjects with FH and to improve health and healthcare delivery. Rare&#xD;
      diseases of lipoprotein metabolism (orphan diseases) will also be included (SMASH registry;&#xD;
      Systems and Molecular Approach of Severe Hyperlipidemia). This registry will include&#xD;
      clinical, biochemical and demographic information. Specimens (plasma/serum and DNA) will be&#xD;
      collected for biobanking. The registry will be made available for clinicians to manage&#xD;
      patient care, identify relatives for screening and treatment (cascade screening), to provide&#xD;
      advice to general practitioners and to support collaborative studies in biomedical, clinical,&#xD;
      health outcomes and health economics research. Access to anonymized data from the registry&#xD;
      will be given to researchers, clinicians, biopharmaceutical industry and government by&#xD;
      peer-reviewed process.&#xD;
&#xD;
      The Mission of the Canadian FH Registry is to bring together a multi-disciplinary group of&#xD;
      physicians, basic and clinical researchers to improve the delivery of care to patients with&#xD;
      severe lipoprotein disorders, especially FH, and to foster collaborative research. Our Vision&#xD;
      is to create a Canada-wide network of academic clinics, integrating lipid specialists,&#xD;
      endocrinologists and cardiologists to treat patients with the highest standard of care and to&#xD;
      create a collaborative research environment. Using a &quot;hub and spoke&quot; model, the registry will&#xD;
      be extended in various communities to link primary care physicians with provincial academic&#xD;
      centers. The Goals are to improve care to patients with FH and to reduce cardiovascular&#xD;
      disease in this population at high risk.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Given the wide geographic distribution of patients with FH, we plan to provide a &quot;hub and&#xD;
      spoke&quot; model specialized care. The hubs would be based in each province in centers recognized&#xD;
      at the national level for their expertise in lipoprotein disorders and with advanced&#xD;
      laboratory facilities (medical biochemistry, specialized assays, ultracentrifugation, genetic&#xD;
      testing). Radiating from these centers will be clinics that treat patients with FH. We&#xD;
      propose a three-tier registry (local, provincial and Canada-wide). The local database would&#xD;
      be nominative, used solely by the clinic or center and contain the information obtained by&#xD;
      the local investigators and used for clinical purposes. The provincial database will use&#xD;
      encrypted numbers, without identifiers other than the provincial health insurance number, and&#xD;
      will be used to generate province-specific health outcomes, resource utilization, health&#xD;
      economics and comparative epidemiological/genetic/clinical features across provinces. The&#xD;
      Canadian database would be anonymous and serve to generate country-wide statistics, public&#xD;
      awareness and research collaborations.&#xD;
&#xD;
      All procedures related to the FH registry will follow uniform standard operation procedures&#xD;
      (SOP). The various steps associated with the inclusion of patients within the FH Registry&#xD;
      will be the following: subject with high LDL-C, secondary causes ruled out, FH Criteria&#xD;
      satisfied, consent form signed, clinical evaluation, baseline lipid profile, demographic&#xD;
      info, family history, longitudinal follow-up (annual data capture). If a patient has a family&#xD;
      history of FH, then we will start cascade screening. If the FH criteria are not satisfied at&#xD;
      the beginning of the study then the patient will be asked to enter in the SMASH registry for&#xD;
      other severe disorders of the lipid metabolism.&#xD;
&#xD;
      The database software should fulfill the following criteria: if must comply with privacy&#xD;
      regulations in all provinces, use passwords that allow limited access, with access tailored&#xD;
      to each site. It must allow researchers access under strictly controlled conditions after&#xD;
      peer-review. The software must be flexible enough to allow easy data entry and capture for&#xD;
      the provincial and Canadian databases. Cost considerations are also an issue. The choice of&#xD;
      software has not been made yet.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Biobanking will be performed at individual sites, when available. Plasma/serum, DNA, tissues&#xD;
      (e.g. skin biopsies) will be potentially included. The consent form will have a specific&#xD;
      section dealing with DNA banking and the possibility that the DNA may be sent to a central&#xD;
      laboratory for analysis. The informed consent will also stipulate that plasma/serum and DNA&#xD;
      samples may be analyzed by academic collaborators outside of Canada and by industry&#xD;
      (pharmaceutical and/or biotechnology).&#xD;
&#xD;
      Data entry at each site will be performed using nominative information and coded specific to&#xD;
      the institution (hospital ID number). In addition, each subject's provincial health insurance&#xD;
      number will be entered and a unique identifier will be assigned (for instance BC_000001;&#xD;
      QC_000001 and so on). As FH is highly familial by nature, parents, sibs and all first-degree&#xD;
      relatives of each subject will also be entered, if known. While each subject will have a&#xD;
      distinct identifier, family relationships will be recorded. Completely anonymous data will be&#xD;
      made available to researchers, policy makers, governments and industry on a per need basis.&#xD;
      Physicians at each site will be able to retrieve the information pertinent to their site&#xD;
      only. Access to the database will be granted after investigators have submitted a written&#xD;
      request to the Scientific Board and clearance will be given in consultation with the Advisory&#xD;
      Board. Both levels of government (provincial and National) will be given similar access, as&#xD;
      will the pharmaceutical industry and the biopharmaceutical industry.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Potential benefits Patients. Patients will have access to expert care in the field of&#xD;
      lipoprotein disorders and CVD prevention. In many cases, optimal treatment of severe&#xD;
      hypercholesterolemia may be best provided by experts in the field. They will have access to&#xD;
      on-going clinical trials and to novel therapies. Furthermore, individual patients will be&#xD;
      offered family screening to identify affected members who would benefit from early diagnosis&#xD;
      and treatment. The identification of new FH cases by cascade screening proves to be both&#xD;
      cost-effective and aligns with the aim of providing personalized medicine for patients with&#xD;
      severe lipoprotein disorders.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Clinicians. The registry will provide the local (i.e. clinic or hospital) framework to&#xD;
      diagnose patients according to accepted international criteria for FH, to follow the subjects&#xD;
      in time and to perform cascade screening (first, second and third-degree relatives), a&#xD;
      cost-effective strategy to screen potentially affected subjects. The registry will also link&#xD;
      clinicians into a network of specialized clinics that favor collaborative&#xD;
      investigator-initiated research and participation in multi-center studies. The availability&#xD;
      of biobanking will allow the storage of plasma/serum and DNA for future research.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Biomedical researchers. The identification of novel genes for FH and other rare lipoprotein&#xD;
      disorders has led to a better understanding of metabolic pathways and eventually the&#xD;
      potential for novel therapeutic targets. In addition, gene-gene and gene-environment&#xD;
      interactions research may shed light on mechanisms of disease. clinical-scientists will have&#xD;
      the opportunity to develop investigator-initiated research, using the pan-Canadian registry&#xD;
      and biobanking resources as a platform. Researchers in health outcomes and health economics,&#xD;
      social, gender and ethnic research will have access to the database in collaboration with&#xD;
      provincial administrative databases.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Biopharmaceutical Industry. The biopharmaceutical industry will have access to a group of&#xD;
      lipid experts across Canada, with links internationally, a harmonized database for subjects&#xD;
      with FH and rare lipoprotein disorders. They will have access to a network of established&#xD;
      clinics with a unified database. Access to the registry database will be provided after&#xD;
      review of the intended research. This data will be important in determining health economics.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Government. This initiative will allow the development of clinical practice guidelines, to&#xD;
      determine resource allocation according to need, the identification of rare (orphan disease)&#xD;
      lipoprotein disorders requiring specific techniques, such as extracorporeal LDL filtration&#xD;
      for homozygous FH. The initiative will allow the framework to set-up collaborative research&#xD;
      under the peer-review system (HSFC, CIHR). Health outcomes and health economic studies will&#xD;
      allow resource allocation and quality control. Finally centralized genetic testing would&#xD;
      provide molecular diagnostics in a cost-effective manner, when required. This initiative will&#xD;
      dovetail with the CIHR C-CHANGE initiative concerning the harmonization of cardiovascular&#xD;
      preventive guidelines in Canada. To data, we are the only country with harmonized CVD&#xD;
      prevention guidelines.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Knowledge translation and training. Individual academic institutions with a strong biomedical&#xD;
      research commitment will offer undergraduate and graduate-level training in the field of&#xD;
      lipid and lipoproteins within a country-wide collaborative research environment. Several&#xD;
      centers will offer post-doctoral fellowships for clinicians and PhDs in lipoprotein&#xD;
      metabolism, health outcomes and health economics research. This training of highly qualified&#xD;
      personnel is expected to contribute to the academic and economic engine of the country. A&#xD;
      formal training course, aligned with the National Lipid Association, will provide&#xD;
      certification on the treatment of lipoprotein disorders. The establishment of clinical&#xD;
      practice guidelines for adult and pediatric patients will enable clinicians to hone their&#xD;
      clinical practice to the highest standard. By using well established conferences across&#xD;
      Canada, the aim will be to integrate novel knowledge into the yearly conference programs&#xD;
      across Canada and to disseminate this information to practicing physicians and health care&#xD;
      professionals.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date>November 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational [Patient Registry]</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <target_duration>15 Years</target_duration>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Patients with FH</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Prevalence rates of FH in Canada</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">6000</enrollment>
  <condition>Familial Hypercholesterolemia</condition>
  <condition>Lipid Disorder</condition>
  <biospec_retention>Samples With DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      Plasma and Buffy coat for DNA extraction DNA stock samples&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Patients from primary care clinics&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
        Diagnostic criteria for FH, which are:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Family and/or personal history of high cholesterol&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Family and/or personal history of heart disease&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Abnormal growth on tendons, accumulation of fatty material in the eye Family history&#xD;
             of FH Severe disorder of cholesterol and other lipids in the blood&#xD;
&#xD;
        Exclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
        No exclusion criterion&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jacques Genest, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Research Institute of the McGill University Health Centre</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Isabelle Ruel, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>514-934-1934</phone>
    <phone_ext>34852</phone_ext>
    <email>isabelle.ruel@mail.mcgill.ca</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Institute of the McGill University Health Centre: Royal Victoria Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Montreal</city>
        <state>Quebec</state>
        <zip>H3A1A1</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Isabelle Ruel, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>514-934-1934</phone>
      <phone_ext>34258</phone_ext>
      <email>isabelle.ruel@mail.mcgill.ca</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jacques Genest, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>June 2014</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>November 21, 2013</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 8, 2013</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">December 12, 2013</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 20, 2014</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 20, 2014</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">June 23, 2014</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>McGill University Health Centre/Research Institute of the McGill University Health Centre</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Jacques Genest</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Familial hypercholesterolemia,</keyword>
  <keyword>High LDL-cholesterol</keyword>
  <keyword>Registry</keyword>
  <keyword>Coronary artery disease</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hyperlipoproteinemia Type II</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hypercholesterolemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lipid Metabolism Disorders</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

